Ruffin/Jones Family Collection 145
People's Archive, MLK Library
Ruffin/Jones Family Collection
1842 - 1999 (bulk 1920s - 1999)
1920-1999
People's Archive, MLK Library
145
4.5 Linear feet
8 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
The Ruffin/Jones Family contains material related to C. Bernard Ruffin, III and members of his family, especially C. Bernard Ruffin, Jr.; Louise Jones Hubbard; and Mary Jones Nightengale Carter.
C. Bernard Ruffin, III is the Pastor at Lutheran Church of the Holy Comforter in Washington, DC. After graduating from Roosevelt High School in DC, he attended Bowdoin College and Yale Divinity School. He served at several other churches prior to becoming Assistant Pastor at Holy Comforter in 1980. Ruffin also worked as a history teacher at South Lakes High School in Reston, VA. He has written and co-written a number of books, including: Padre Pio: The True Story; The Shroud of Turin; The Twelve: The Lives of the Apostles after Calvary; Miracles of St. Padre Pio; The Days of the Martyrs: A History of the Persecution of Christians from Apostolic Times to the Time of Constantine; The Life of Brother Andre: The Miracle Worker of St. Joseph; Last Words: A Dictionary of Deathbed Quotations; and Profiles in Faith: The Religious Beliefs of Eminent Americans.
C. Bernard Ruffin, Jr. (father of C. Bernard Ruffin, III) grew up in Washington, DC and attended Howard University. He was a Metropolitan Police Officer from 1940 until 1964. He was also head of Division Two of the Metropolitan Police Boys Club from 1952 to 1958, as well as Director of the Police Boys Club Summer Camp from 1950 to 1958. He went on to serve as the Director of Safety and Security at Howard University, the Associate Director of the Pilot Police Project, and the Security Director at Montgomery College.
Lillian Jones Ruffin (mother of C. Bernard Ruffin, III), came from a large family from Chambersburg, PA. Her parents, Lewis and Sarah Jones, had fourteen children in total. Four of these children -- Lillian, Louise, Mary, and Amy -- ended up living in Washington, DC.
Louise Jones Hubbard attended Howard University, Columbia University, and Catholic University. In addition to writing a book and many articles on foreign languages and the teaching of foreign languages, she taught at Bluefield State College, Dunbar High School, District of Columbia Teachers College (now the University of the District of Columbia), and the University of Benin. Louise was a member of the Fifteenth Street Presbyterian Church and Delta Sigma Theta Sorority.
Mary Jones Nightengale Carter attended Howard University, Columbia University, the University of Chicago, and the University of Iowa. She taught business at Terrell Junior High School, Dunbar High School, and Roosevelt High School. Mary was a member of St. Anthony's Catholic Church, as well as the Woofs Club.
Custodial History
The Ruffin/Jones Family Collection was donated to the Library by C. Bernard Ruffin, III
Scope and Contents
The Ruffin/Jones Family Collection contains photographs, cassette tapes with audio recordings of interviews, and printed material such as articles and publications, brochures and programs, school-related items, letters, and research files and notes pertaining to C. Bernard Ruffin, III and members of his family. The life and work of his aunt, Louise Jones Hubbard, is particularly well-documented; material related to her makes up a large portion of the collection.
The collection is divided into seven (7) series: I. Louise Hubbard; II. C. Bernard Ruffin, Jr.; III. C. Bernard Ruffin, III; IV. Mary Carter; V. Ruffin/Jones Family, General; VI. Photographs; and VII. Audio. Series I., Louise Hubbard, is divided into four (4) sub-series: I. Articles and Publications; II. Church; III. Groups and Extracurricular Activities; and IV. Teaching.
African Americans; Genealogy; City churches; Families; Black people
- Series 1
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baseball Drawing, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Class Record Book, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DC Teachers College Catalog - 1971/1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fifteenth Street Presbyterian Church, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fifteenth Street Presbyterian Church, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women in Mongo Betti's Perpetu, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Boys Club, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Award Night Program, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Louise Hubbard, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Presbyterian Church Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dunbar High School, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class Register Books, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Club Members Fold Christmas Seals, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dunbar High School Newsletter, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - All College Assembly / Travel Abroad, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Class Record Books, 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fifteenth Street Presbyterian Church, 1953-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Academic Consolidation Committee, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fifteenth Street Presbyterian Church 150th Anniversary Planning Committee, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Historical Committee/ History Notes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Presbyterian Women, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Howard Transcript, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Board Pamphlet, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - English Teaching Forum Magazine, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Modern Language Journal, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Accent on ACTFL, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Division of Foreign Languages and Literature, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript - Morceaux Choisis, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Modern Language Journal, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript - Hubbard, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Foreign Language Annals Journal, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Individual and the Group in French Literature since 1914. Dissertation, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Delta Journal, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ACTFL Workshop Proceedings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Spanish in the Elementary Schools, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1978 MLA International Bibliography, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annales de L'Universite du Benin, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The DFL Bulletin, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Public Schools of DC Curriculum Bulletin, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University of Congo Pamphlet, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - CLA Journal - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The College Faculty Portraits, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Strength through Wisdom: A Critique of U.S Capability, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Dimension Languages '80 16th Southern Conference on Language Teaching, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Guide for Teaching Spanish in the Elementary Schools, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)